On the 5th of November, 1991,
the body of the Czechoslovak-born
British publishing tycoon Robert Maxwell
was retrieved from the Atlantic Ocean,
floating off the Canary Islands.
Investigations initially suggested that
Maxwell had drowned after suffering a
heart attack and falling into the water
from his yacht, the Lady Ghislaine.
But, in the months that followed,
suspicions arose that Maxwell had taken
his own life.
His business empire had been on the
verge of collapse, and he was facing
criminal charges.
What crimes had Maxwell allegedly been
engaged in, and did he really take his
own life?
This is the story of Robert Maxwell,
Britain's most notorious media tycoon.
The man known to history as Robert
Maxwell was born on the 10th of June,
1923,
in the small town of Slatinské Doly,
which was then in Czechoslovakia, but
which is now the town of Solotvino in
the far west of Ukraine along the border
with Romania.
Maxwell's name during his childhood was
Ján Ludvík Hoch Benjamin Hoch. The name
by which he is known today, Ian Robert
Maxwell, was adopted later in his life
after settling in Britain.
Ján's father was Mechel Hoch, a farm
laborer.
His mother was Hanna Hoch.
The family were poor Hasidic Jews who
lived within a large Jewish community in
Slatinské Doly.
Jan was one of nine siblings, several of
whom died in infancy owing to the
poverty in which the family lived.
Jan's youth was not easy
and his life only became more difficult
in his teenage and young adult years.
The family was poor and anti-Semitism
was at its most virulent in Europe
during the interwar era, albeit there
were worse countries to live in from a
Jewish perspective than Czechoslovakia.
Their home was a two-room house with
beds arranged in one room and a latrine
outside serving as a bathroom.
His mother doted on him,
but his father beat him regularly.
Maxwell later reflected of his childhood
years that the three things which he
remembered from it were how cold I was,
how hungry I was,
and how much I loved my mother.
His recollections do have to be treated
with some skepticism.
While there is no doubt that the Hochs
were extremely poor, Maxwell grew up to
become an inveterate liar as an adult
and there is no way of knowing if his
description of his childhood was
truthful
or not.
We do know that the family lived in a
melting pot of cultures, languages, and
religions.
After the collapse of the
Austro-Hungarian Empire in 1918,
Slatinské Doly found itself at the
crossroads of Ukraine, Czechoslovakia,
Romania, and Hungary.
Living here ensured that Jan developed
an immense capacity for speaking and
understanding multiple languages from a
young age, an ability that would serve
him well in his later years.
As well as Yiddish and Slovak, he spoke
Czech, Hungarian, French, Russian,
German, and English.
He achieved this despite only having 3
years of formal schooling.
The Great Depression in the 1930s
meant that he worked from a very young
age.
Then came the rise of the Nazis in
Germany and the steady descent into the
Second World War from 1935 onwards as
conflicts broke out from Spain to
Ethiopia to China,
and then in Poland in 1939.
The lives of the Hoch family were
disrupted even before the war broke out
when the Nazis annexed Czechoslovakia in
March 1939
and began imposing the anti-Jewish
Nuremberg laws in the newly conquered
territory.
Less than a year later, 16-year-old Jan
was in Marseille serving with the
Czechoslovak resistance in the Battle of
France.
After the rapid German conquest of
Western Europe, he headed to Britain
where his skill as a linguist ensured
that he quickly rose to become a
sergeant.
In what was probably the finest hour of
his life, he served with distinction in
France in 1944 after the D-Day landings
and was later awarded the Military
Cross.
After the war though, there was no
family to go back to.
His parents and four of his siblings
died in Hungary in 1944,
the deadliest year of the Holocaust
there after the Nazis largely took over
direct control of the country in the
last stages of the Second World War.
The exact plight of some of the Hawks is
hard to track.
For instance, Jan's 19-year-old sister
disappeared in Budapest late in 1944.
She may have been one of the 20,000
Jewish people in the city and
surrounding area who were executed by
the Danube
and thrown into the river.
His parents and other family members
were killed at the Auschwitz death camp.
After the war ended, Jan, who legally
adopted the name Ian Robert Maxwell in
1948,
lived between Britain and Germany.
For many years, post-1945
Germany was under Allied occupation.
War trials were underway, and there was
a very complicated array of post-war
reconstruction measures being initiated.
The entire country had to be denazified
and rebuilt from scratch, including the
media, which had effectively been a
branch of National Socialism between
and 1945.
Maxwell's abilities as a translator
meant he was in high demand in this
complex post-war German environment.
He was appointed to the Berlin
Information Control Unit and worked as
part of the Control Commission for
Germany.
This was a commission associated with
the director of the press and publicity
branch of the British Information
Service, a complicated name for the
British body established to redevelop
the media system in their part of
occupied Germany and Berlin.
Maxwell was specifically employed to
reestablish the paper named Der
Berliner,
which was later renamed as Der Telegraph
in the British zone of Berlin.
Papers like this were carefully managed
to keep the Allied message on point
after the war.
The Nazi leadership were being
prosecuted for having led Germany so
astray, but if the German people agreed
to reform themselves, then they would be
welcomed back into the community of
Europe's nations.
Maxwell's job was logistical to a large
extent.
There were huge post-war shortages of
everything in Germany, and he spent a
lot of his time in Berlin ensuring that
Der Telegraph had enough ink and paper
to be printed, as well as petrol to run
generators to power the printing
presses.
He worked with the major German printer,
Ferdinand Springer, on some publishing
ventures.
Maxwell also married Elizabeth Menard in
1945,
a French woman whom Robert met in France
after the liberation of the country in
1944.
They were to have nine children over the
next 16 years,
four sons named Michael, Philip, Ian,
and Kevin, and five daughters, Anne,
Christine, Isabelle, Karine, and
Ghislaine.
As we will see, Ghislaine has become
notorious today, but back in the 1990s,
it was Robert's sons, Ian and Kevin, who
were in the public eye after being
implicated in their father's crimes.
Maxwell became a naturalized British
citizen in 1946,
and he and Elizabeth lived in Britain
with Robert traveling back and forth
between his adopted homeland and
Germany.
Maxwell's future career was shaped by
his experiences in Central Europe.
There, he became involved in the early
formation of Butterworth Springer, an
academic publishing company which was
driven by Springer's know-how in the
field, transferring into war German
ideas about academic publishing to
post-war Britain.
The company's headquarters were
established in England in 1948,
operating between London and Oxford in
order to be in close proximity to the
university there.
In 1951,
Maxwell acquired a controlling interest
in the company, and its name was changed
to Pergamon Press.
The Pergamon imprint is still a going
concern to this day and is a leader in
academic publishing in Britain, though
now it is a subsidiary of Elsevier, a
major conglomerate in the sector.
Maxwell was responsible for building it
up into a major player in publishing
academic books, journals, and reports in
post-war Britain, eventually publishing
hundreds of different journals that
produced thousands of research articles
every year.
It also became the publisher to the Club
of Rome, the Italian think tank that
produced a number of prominent books in
the late 1960s and early 1970s
about the future economic trajectory of
Europe.
In 1958 with Pergamon reaching a new
level of success and money coming in,
Maxwell acquired the lease of Headington
Hill Hall in Oxfordshire.
This was an early sign of his desire to
live the high life even before he was
making truly large sums of money.
Headington Hill Hall was built back in
the 1820s by James Morrell, the head of
a wealthy family of brewers in Oxford.
It was an elegant Italianate manor house
replete with large columns around the
exterior, balconies for the upstairs
rooms, a huge staircase entryway up to
the main doors, and all set on a large
forested estate.
Many a major Victorian and early 20th
century high society event had been
hosted there before the Morrells sold
the estate to Oxford City Council in
1953.
By that time, it was relatively
run-down, having served as a military
hospital during the war.
The council had been considering
demolishing it and redeveloping the
estate before Maxwell acquired a 32-year
lease of the 51-bedroom house and the
surrounding estate.
Robert and his family lived there for
the rest of his life in a home that was
replete with a swimming pool and a
tennis court, while Maxwell moved some
of Pergamon's operations to the house
and in later years had a helipad set up
on the vast lawns so that he could fly
in and out of London quickly for
business meetings.
Maxwell once described it as "The best
council house in the country."
The property is currently leased to
Oxford Brookes University.
While Maxwell was professionally
successful during these years, tragedy
was never far from his personal life.
In 1957,
Karine, Robert and Elisabeth's
3-year-old daughter, was diagnosed with
leukemia and she died not long
afterwards.
Then, in the final week of 1961,
their 15-year-old son, Michael, ended up
in a coma after a car crash when his
driver lost control and hit another
vehicle head-on.
He never regained consciousness and died
7 years later.
Biographers have suggested that
Maxwell's fondness for his youngest
daughter, Ghislaine,
may have been owing to the fact that she
was born on Christmas Day, 1961,
2 days before Michael's car crash, and
he focused his energies on raising her
after the tragedies of recent years.
The impact on his older children was
brutal.
Maxwell became an overbearing father,
especially towards his sons, physically
disciplining them and becoming paranoid
about their safety.
Maxwell's psychology and life
experiences have to be kept in mind in
any assessment of him as a father and as
a businessman.
He came from terrible poverty,
ended up fighting in the war when he was
16 years old, lost virtually his entire
family in the Holocaust, and then lost
two children in a series of further
family tragedies between 1957
and 1967.
In 1964,
Maxwell entered politics.
The United Kingdom had gone through a
series of emergencies in the late 1950s
and early 1960s,
including the Suez Crisis of 1956
that heralded the collapse of Britain's
colonial empire in Africa, and domestic
crises like the Profumo affair.
This resulted in a swift turnover of
Conservative leaders and several general
elections.
Alec Douglas-Home called fresh elections
in 1964,
and Maxwell was recruited to stand for
election in the constituency of
Buckingham as the Labour Party
candidate.
He won election in October that year,
while Harold Wilson became the new Prime
Minister leading the Labour Party back
into government.
Maxwell was reelected in the 1966
election after Wilson called a snap
election to benefit from a surge in
popularity for his party.
But, in 1970,
as Labour suffered a surprise defeat,
Maxwell was one of the Labour Party MPs
who lost his seat.
He made over 700 contributions in the
House of Commons during his six years as
an MP, but ultimately his parliamentary
career was undistinguished.
A major concern of his was the move to
split the old British Museum into two
distinct bodies, the British Museum and
the new British Library.
This project came to fruition in 1973
after Maxwell had left Parliament.
In 1968,
Maxwell attempted and failed to buy the
tabloid The News of the World, Britain's
biggest-selling Sunday newspaper.
The owners of the paper, the Carr
family, were incensed by the prospect of
it being owned by a Czechoslovak
immigrant with socialist views.
The paper's editor at the time, Stafford
Somerfield, wrote a front-page opinion
piece in which he said that The News of
the World was a British paper run by
British people, as British as roast beef
and Yorkshire pudding. Let us keep it
that way.
The newspaper was later bought by the
Australian tycoon and media rival Rupert
Murdoch.
In 1969, while he was still a sitting
member of Parliament, Maxwell faced the
first major crisis of his publishing
career.
This involved the Leasco Data Processing
Corporation headed by Saul Steinberg.
Steinberg, an American businessman, had
made a fortune in the 1960s from leasing
out some of the earliest computer models
on the market to institutions before the
age of personal computing really
accelerated in the 1970s.
In the late 1960s, Steinberg was
aggressively buying up businesses, and
he became interested in acquiring
Pergamon.
He approached Maxwell with a large
offer, and Maxwell was not opposed to
selling, especially so because Pergamon
had expanded in an aggressive manner in
the 1960s and was facing cash flow
problems by 1969.
However, the negotiations became
problematic after Robert provided
information to Steinberg, which
exaggerated the profitability of the
company, particularly its sales of
encyclopedias.
When Steinberg revealed this, Pergamon
was suspended from operating on the
London Stock Exchange owing to concerns
over share price manipulation by
Maxwell.
A five-year-long battle ensued in which
Maxwell lost his position on the board,
and he had to fight to reclaim control
over the company from Steinberg, who had
also come under investigation in the US
for his aggressive business expansion
practices.
Maxwell only survived the Leasco scandal
and reclaimed control over Pergamon
after the heads of many of the most
important journals in the company's
portfolio insisted that their continued
involvement with the company was
conditional on Maxwell returning as
chairman.
On the one hand, people who had known
and worked with Maxwell for years were
aware that he was an effective
businessman in the field.
Conversely, there was no denying that
his behavior had fallen well short of
typical ethical standards.
He had sought to manipulate the value of
the company to get Steinberg to pay
significantly over the odds.
When the protracted fallout from the
Leasco scandal came to an end in 1974,
Britain was entering into a prolonged
economic crisis following from the 1973
oil crisis.
Even so, Maxwell pressed ahead with
expanding Pergamon.
He moved into the publication of
computer science journals in the 1970s,
predicting how personal computing was
about to lead to a boom in that field.
Maxwell was also one of the first major
academic publishers to foresee that
databases of journals and articles would
shape the industry in the future.
He was entirely correct.
Academic publishing is dominated today
by databases of hundreds of journals,
rather than individual publications.
His ambitions were expanding, too.
In the 1970s, he began moving more
aggressively into print media, and in
1981, he acquired the British Printing
Corporation.
This was a foretaste of the extremely
rapid manner in which he built up one of
Britain's most important media empires
in the 1980s.
This would ultimately prove to be his
undoing as he tried to expand far too
quickly, and all of his worst
personality traits came to the fore.
Maxwell courted controversy throughout
his life.
He also became a magnet for conspiracy
theories that frequently contradicted
each other.
As a Jewish man who had lost most of his
family in the Holocaust, he was a firm
supporter of the state of Israel when it
declared independence in 1948, and
remained so throughout his life, later
using his media influence to promote
Israel's cause in Britain.
A number of studies have gone further,
arguing that Maxwell was effectively an
agent of Mossad, the Israeli secret
services, over many years.
He did have a background in clandestine
work.
Immediately after the war, while he was
working for the British in Germany, he
was occasionally called upon to take
part in interrogations owing to his
linguistic abilities.
The inference is that he had
associations with MI6, and this brought
him to the attention of Mossad, who
asked him to begin spying for them in
Britain. While another theory suggests
that Maxwell acted as an intermediary
between weapons traders in
Czechoslovakia and Israel in 1948
as the fledgling state tried to acquire
extra weapons at a time when many
Western countries were wary of its
decision to declare independence.
Later, more elaborate theories emerged,
including the notion that Maxwell helped
the Israeli government distribute a spy
software known as Promise to Western
countries, and that he was also
connected to intelligence gathering for
Israel's nuclear weapons program.
Certainly, the British Foreign Office
considered it likely that Maxwell's ties
to the Israeli government were
sufficient that he could be classified
as a foreign agent. While Maxwell also
invested heavily in Israel and owned
many businesses there.
Beyond this, he was suspected at various
times of potentially being a KGB asset
and of having connections to the Soviet
regime going all the way back to his
time in Germany immediately after the
war.
One lengthy book has even argued that
Maxwell was involved in running a
complex network of criminal enterprises
that extended into Eastern Europe with
strong connections to the Bulgarian
underworld in particular.
Many of these claims are unlikely.
Others are much more plausible.
By the start of the 1980s, Maxwell
appeared to be a very wealthy man,
largely based from his astute management
of Pergamon.
It was at this juncture that his
ambitions expanded.
He wanted to become a second Rupert
Murdoch, the Australian who had muscled
his way into the British media landscape
and become a dominant figure within it.
Wishing to rise to a position of equal
prominence, in 1984,
Maxwell purchased the Mirror Group for
113 million pounds, the flagship of
which was the Daily Mirror, a
sensationalist daily newspaper that had
become the best-selling paper in Britain
in the 1960s, peaking with average sales
of 5 million copies a day at that time.
By 1984,
it was facing stiffer competition, and
Maxwell acquired it along with other
titles in the Mirror Group like the
Sunday Mirror and The Sporting Life.
Maxwell convened the board's first
meeting in 1984 after he bought the
group at 2:45 a.m. and declared that he
wanted total control over the papers'
finances, an ominous sign of things to
come.
Thereafter, he followed up on his
ambitions to rival Murdoch by launching
The European and acquiring the New York
Daily News, a financially troubled US
newspaper.
He also continued to expand the rest of
his publishing empire in the 1980s by
acquiring Macmillan Inc., one of the
world's largest publishers, the $2.6
million
in 1988.
This was a significant move.
It proved ultimately beyond Maxwell's
financial capacity and would play a role
in his downfall in the years that
followed.
Maxwell had business interests beyond
publishing and the media.
In 1982, he became the owner of his own
football team, which was unusual in
British football at the time.
Today, English football teams are
billion-pound businesses overseen by
extremely wealthy families and even
nation-states
with season tickets costing thousands of
pounds and matches played on pristine
pitches.
In 1982,
there was a more rugged element to
football and the money men had not yet
taken over.
Ken Bates famously bought Chelsea
Football Club for £1 the same year that
Maxwell acquired a controlling interest
in Oxford United Football Club.
The club dated back to 1893
and was prominent locally, but it was
facing bankruptcy in 1982 and was
languishing in the old third division
when Maxwell stepped in and rescued it
from insolvency.
His takeover became controversial the
following year when he put forward a
proposal to unite Oxford with Reading
Football Club to form a new super club
called Thames Valley Royals.
Maxwell owned 18% of Reading and
geographically the two clubs were
located near each other.
However, a merger like this was unheard
of and was opposed by fans of both
teams.
It never materialized.
Surprisingly, Oxford then went on to
enjoy a golden age.
Under Maxwell's stewardship, they won
the third division in 1984 and repeated
the feat in the second division the next
year. This brought them into the first
division where they remained for nearly
a full decade, even winning the League
Cup in 1986.
After Maxwell's death, the club became
insolvent and plummeted down the
divisions and into the less prestigious
Conference League.
Maxwell was known for his scandalous
behavior, his love of money, his many
affairs, and his eccentricities.
Legend has it that he once gave his wife
a list of six rules for a perfect
marriage, which included advice not to
nag or criticize.
Robert spent large amounts of time
living in London near his mistresses in
later years.
The full extent of his eccentricities
and extreme behavior was only revealed
after his death in numerous biographies
and articles that quoted journalists and
editors who had worked for Maxwell over
the years.
For instance, the Labour Party's
strategist and fixer under Tony Blair's
New Labour government, Alastair
Campbell, recalled visiting Ethiopia in
in the middle of a well-documented
famine there.
Maxwell appeared to give an address
before the press there as though he was
a world leader.
He then left without telling anybody,
instead leaving behind a note saying,
"My work here is done. I've gone back to
London to resolve the miners' strike."
A reference to the standoff between
Britain's Prime Minister Margaret
Thatcher and the miners' unions in
Britain in 1984.
Maxwell had nothing to do with the
negotiations surrounding it.
Family dramas and disputes were common,
and he notoriously was a ferocious bully
to his staff.
Perhaps the most scandalous story of all
was that Maxwell allegedly used to
urinate off the top of the Daily
Mirror's office building off Fleet
Street in London onto the streets of the
capital below before climbing into his
helicopter.
Maxwell's life and career would come to
a premature end in a haze of scandal and
conspiracy in 1991.
In 1990, a number of journalists had
begun to look into the financial affairs
of the holding company which many of
Maxwell's businesses operated under,
Maxwell Communication Corporation PLC.
Certain transactions had aroused
suspicions about his dealings.
For instance, a press release in 1990
announced that Maxwell was due to sell
some of his Italian publishing
subsidiaries for 60 million pounds, but
when it was investigated, it was
revealed that there was no such deal and
Maxwell was almost certainly announcing
the sale in a bid to create market
confidence about the viability of his
businesses in light of the huge amount
of debt he had taken on to expand in the
1980s, notably with the massive outlay
for Macmillan and the New York Daily
News.
As further investigations occurred, it
became apparent that Maxwell had been
using a range of methods to prop up his
struggling empire.
He had created millions of shares for
the Maxwell Communication Corporation
and then passed them to family members.
Another regulator in Britain began
looking into Maxwell's technology
portfolio and determined that Maxwell's
companies were effectively using
hundreds of different types of software
illegally.
Most nefariously of all, it would soon
be revealed that he was illegally
utilizing hundreds of millions of pounds
from the Mirror Group's pension funds to
support his companies and save them from
bankruptcy.
This had been done secretly and without
authorization.
Clearly, the stress of the double life
he was leading as a wildly successful
media magnate in public and a distressed
fraudster juggling money illegally to
keep his empire afloat in private was
taking its toll.
Maxwell had always been a man of heavy
appetites, but as the 1990s began, his
weight increased further as he took to
eating gargantuan meals and drinking
alcohol throughout the day, sedating
himself with sleeping pills and
painkillers at night to stave off the
pneumonia and other health problems that
he was suffering from.
In March 1991, Pergamon, the jewel in
the Maxwell empire, was sold for 440
million pounds.
Even this could only buy Maxwell a few
months of breathing room.
By the late autumn of 1991, he knew
matters were coming to a head.
Regulators were investigating his
financial affairs thoroughly, and he had
no further leeway to try to manipulate
the corporation's share price.
He knew that a series of meetings in
London in November 1991 would spell the
end of the long ruse.
It was in this context that Maxwell
headed for Gibraltar at the end of
October 1991,
where his yacht, the Lady Ghislaine, was
being repaired.
He rang ahead to tell his staff to have
the boat ready to take him south to
Madeira and the Canary Islands, as he
hoped that the warmer air would shake
his cold.
Maxwell behaved strangely during this
trip.
Usually, he would be accompanied by
staff bringing half a dozen suitcases
stuffed with papers and tins of caviar,
and driven to the airport in his
Rolls-Royce, but on this occasion, he
traveled with little fanfare.
Staff who did interact with him in the
days that followed remember thinking
that he seemed surprisingly jovial.
Everyone knew that he was in dire
financial straits by then, so this was
regarded as surprising.
After a trip south to Madeira, his yacht
headed for the Canaries.
The 4th of November came and went. A
date on which Maxwell was supposed to
have met with his creditors in London
over an unpaid debt of 50 million
pounds.
That evening, Maxwell spoke to his son,
Kevin, on the phone and was overheard
arguing with him about a scheduled
meeting with the Bank of England.
And then, at some time around 5:00 a.m.
or 6:00 a.m. on the morning of the 5th
of November, 1991,
he fell into the Atlantic Ocean and
drowned.
There are multiple theories about what
might have happened to Maxwell, ranging
from the plausible to the ludicrous.
It is quite conceivable, for instance,
that Maxwell was urinating off the side
of the ship and slipped into the water.
Or, that he was simply wandering around
on the deck and fell off after having a
heart attack.
This theory was favored by many people
at the time and has been argued for in
many books and news articles ever since.
The idea here is that Maxwell died
because of a fairly typical boating
accident.
An aging man fell into the water and
drowned.
Others elaborate on this and claim that
there were additional circumstances that
led to him falling into the sea and
being unable to pull himself back out.
For example, it has been theorized that
he was suffering from food poisoning, as
investigations did reveal that he had
consumed clams at the Hotel Mencey about
9 hours before he fell into the sea.
Alternatively, speculators who were more
inclined towards conspiracy theories
claimed that he could have been
poisoned.
Maxwell certainly did have a lot of
enemies.
Moreover, this theory gained a lot of
credence after Maxwell's death because
both the forensic Institute of Las
Palmas in the Canary Islands and the
Spanish Toxicology Institute in Madrid
refused to state they could rule out
some form of foul play.
Even more outlandish were ideas that
Maxwell had been killed by the KGB or
the East German Stasi or even by a rival
newspaper baron.
One theory even holds that Maxwell
staged the whole thing, that the body
that was discovered was not his, and
that he went off to lead a different
life in secret after staging his own
death.
The most obvious explanation tends to be
the most credible.
There seems little doubt when the dire
financial circumstances he was in are
considered and the fact that he was
looking at time in prison once his
illegal use of the Mirror Group's
pension funds was revealed that Maxwell
had decided to take his own life.
Still, the debate raged for months about
what had happened to him.
His family denied that he would have
jumped into the ocean.
His wife, Betty, from whom he was
completely estranged during the last
year of his life, insisted he would not
have taken his own life.
The initial reaction to his death was a
deluge of sympathetic eulogies.
The British Prime Minister at the time,
John Major, lauded his role not only as
a publisher and newspaperman, but as a
point of contact between the British
government and foreign countries where
Maxwell had contacts.
Margaret Thatcher called him a unique
figure in British life.
These positive accounts in Britain
aside, Maxwell was laid to rest in
Israel, his hero's farewell having the
air of a quasi state event when it was
held on the Mount of Olives in Jerusalem
on the 10th of November, 1991.
Meanwhile, the investigations continued
in England.
In the course of 1992,
the full scale of Maxwell's market
manipulation was revealed.
One wry account later suggested that by
1991,
there were only two shareholders in
Maxwell's company,
Maxwell himself and Goldman Sachs.
The real issue, though, was the illegal
use of the Mirror Group's pension fund.
Even with Robert dead, somebody had to
be held to account for this, and his two
sons who had been most closely involved
with him in running the businesses, Ian
and Kevin, were arrested in June 1992.
They were ultimately acquitted, but all
of Maxwell's businesses were sold off to
try to repay his debts and reimburse
former staff for the money he had
stolen.
Although his family's wealth, business
empire, and reputation were left in
tatters after his death, the businesses
that Maxwell had built up during his
lifetime continued as going concerns in
various guises.
At the time that Elsevier acquired
Pergamon in May 1991 for 440 million
pounds, it consisted of 418
different academic journals, had over
3,000 books in print, managed the
publications for around 150 different
organizations,
and was affiliated with 100 scientific
and academic societies.
Beyond its base in the United Kingdom,
it had offices in the US, in Canada, in
North America, and in Germany,
Australia, Japan, South Africa, Brazil,
India, Israel, Hong Kong, and South
Korea.
The end of the Cold War was creating
expanded markets in places like China
and the Soviet Union as well.
Today, it continues as an imprint of the
Dutch academic publisher Elsevier, which
is one of the world's largest academic
publishers with an annual revenue of
over $1 billion.
However, some of Maxwell's newspapers
did not outlive him for long.
The European was taken over by the
billionaire Barclay brothers.
Despite heavy investment to try and turn
its fortunes around under the editorial
leadership of Andrew Neil, the
publication of the paper was terminated
in 1998.
The viable papers within the Mirror
Group merged with Trinity International
Holdings in 1999,
an organization that owned the Liverpool
Echo to become Trinity Mirror.
It has been known as Reach PLC since
and continues to publish the Daily
Mirror and other key papers of Maxwell's
former empire.
Thus, while Maxwell corruptly mismanaged
his businesses into the ground in the
1980s, large parts of it remained alive
as viable concerns once they came under
new ownership.
Few people were as well known in media
circles in post-war Britain than Robert
Maxwell.
Nonetheless, after the controversy
surrounding his death and the wreckage
of his business empire passed from
recent memory in the 1990s,
he faded to a degree from the public's
memory, eclipsed by Rupert Murdoch's
dominance of the media in Britain in the
1990s and 2000s.
What's strange is that there has been a
renewed scrutiny of his career in recent
years, not because of his own
controversial behavior, but because of
the daughter after whom his boat was
named.
Ghislaine was, like her other siblings,
left in a peculiar situation after their
father's death.
She had been a socialite in her 20s in
the 1980s and had worked for her father.
It would be inaccurate to suggest that
the collapse of her father's business
empire left her destitute.
The Maxwells had enough money that
remained untouched by the authorities
that she was able to live in an affluent
manner after she relocated to the United
States in 1992,
where she began a relationship with the
financier Jeffrey Epstein, which was
underway by 1993 or 1994.
The chronology is unclear in places, but
it's evident that over the next quarter
of a century she played a central role
in Epstein's affairs.
Before long, this included identifying
underage girls who were groomed on
behalf of Epstein.
This activity went on into the 2000s
before Epstein was eventually convicted
of soliciting a minor for prostitution
in a Florida court in 2008.
On that occasion, Epstein escaped with a
strangely lenient sentence, but in 2019,
he was re-arrested and charged with the
trafficking of minors.
Epstein died in prison not long
afterwards.
Ghislaine was arrested in the summer of
2020 and charged for her role in
Epstein's activities.
In December 2021, she was sentenced to
20 years in prison.
She had rarely been out of the news
since as questions linger about her
former partner's links to many of the
most prominent individuals in American
and international politics, finance, and
business over the last 40 years.
Robert Maxwell was one of the most
important media magnates of the second
half of the 20th century.
While he never acquired the kind of
power and influence that Rupert Murdoch
was able to wield, he was not far away
from attaining that status. Although
ultimately, his attempts to reach the
same heights as Murdoch was Maxwell's
undoing.
His life started far from England in a
Jewish community in the borderland
between Ukraine, Slovakia, Hungary, and
Romania.
He lost most of his family in the
Holocaust during the Second World War
while serving in the Czech resistance
abroad himself.
After the war, he became involved in the
academic publishing industry while
working for the British government in
Allied Occupied Germany. From there, he
moved into the media industry in
Britain. He had a multi-pronged career
in the decades that followed, even
sitting in Parliament for 6 years
between 1964 and 1970.
Academic publishing remained the sphere
in which he had the most success, but
Maxwell became known in public for his
ownership of leading British newspapers
such as the Daily Mirror, as well as his
flamboyant lifestyle at Headington Hill
Hall and the ownership of Oxford United.
Underneath the success, though, was a
mirage.
Maxwell had built a large amount of his
success and opulence by the late 1980s
on corrupt mismanagement of the Mirror
Group's pension funds.
Just as the full extent of his
wrongdoing was about to become known, he
mysteriously fell into the water from
his boat off the coast of the Canary
Islands and drowned.
His media empire collapsed within weeks.
There will always be a debate as to what
happened to Maxwell on the Lady
Ghislaine that November morning in 1991,
but the overwhelming likelihood, given
what was about to be revealed about his
conduct, is that Maxwell took his own
life.
What do you think of Robert Maxwell?
Do you think he drowned after having a
heart attack, or did he take his own
life in awareness that his wrongdoings
were about to come to light?
Please, let us know in the comments
section.
And in the meantime, thank you very much
for watching.
>> Mhm.